[MUSIC PLAYING]
(DING) [MUSIC PLAYING]
[SOUND EFFECTS]
欢迎大家来到这期 Supercharged TL  DW
PAUL LEWIS: Welcome to this Supercharged TL;DW.
我是 Paul
I'm Paul.
上周我和 Surma 直播了
If you didn't catch the livestream with me [? and Serma ?] last week,
如何制作一个边栏导航（side nav）
well, basically we built a side nav.
如果你错过了上周的直播  我将再次展示那个导航效果
Let me show you what we built. So you've got your standard app
这有个标准的 app bar
bar here.
点击侧边栏
You click on this sidebar.
也可以点击背景
And you click on the background, or you
或者像这样  拖拽手势也能让它消失
can dismiss it with a sort of drag gesture, like that.
很酷
Awesome stuff.
你将会知道怎么做出这样的侧边栏
So let me show you how we built it.
但依照惯例  在此之前
But before we do that, as usual, we're
让我们到 Theory Corner
going to head over to-- yep, you guessed it-- Theory Corner!
分析原理
Join me.
Hello
Hello.
欢迎再次来到 Theory Corner
Welcome back to Theory Corner.
我们有一个页面
So this is what we've got.
还有一个容器元素
We've got our page, and we've got a container element.
将侧边栏和背景放在
The container element is going to be the home for the side
容器元素中
nav and the background.
首先  我们要为容器元素
What we're going to do, first of all,
加上 overflow hidden
is we're going to put overflow hidden on this.
还要保证容器的宽高都是 100%
And we're going to make it take up 100% width and height.
加上 overflow hidden 的原因
So it's got overflow hidden because this
是为了侧边栏移出屏幕的时候
is going to transform out to the side,
不会出现滚动条
and we don't want any scrollbars.
所以设置这个属性
So we put that in place.
我们还需要对背景的透明度设置 transition
The background, we're just going to transition its opacity
透明度从 0 到 1
from 0 up to 1.
背景的颜色可以是全透明的黑色
And we'll set it to have a transparent black color,
或者是半透明的黑色
or semi-transparent black color, in the background.
还有侧边栏
The other thing is the side nav.
我们希望它是从侧边滑入的
We want this to slide in from the side,
也就是说  侧边栏要在独立的层中
so we need to have will-change transform on it
所以它的 will-change 属性值为 transform
so that it gets its own layer.
和 Swipeable Cards （另一个 demo）上做的类似
Very much like we did with the swipeable cards.
我们可以轻松滑动侧栏了
And then we can transform it in and out.
还需要一些按钮  触发侧边栏的滑入和滑出
We're also going to need some buttons for bringing it in and out.
再绑定一些 touch 事件
And we're going to have to have some touch events so that we
实现手势操作
can do the dragging stuff.
超酷吧
All cool?
现在让我们回到现实
Let's go back to reality!
欢迎回到现实
Welcome back to reality.
Oh  对
Oh, yes.
是的
Yes.
就是现实
Reality.
我们生活
That's where you'll find us today.
实用才是关键
Pragmatic to the end.
看代码吧
Code.
好的
OK.
html 和 css 和我们在
So the markup and the CSS is pretty much
Theory Corner 中说的差不多
what we discussed in Theory Corner.
有一个侧边栏
We've gotten aside.
有一些用作 JS 钩子的类名
We've got a few JS classes here so that we can pick it up
方便在 JS 中调用
in the JavaScript.
这部分内容大多如你所想
But mostly it's pretty much what you'd expect.
有一个按钮用于关闭侧栏
There's a button for closing.
用另一个按钮拉开侧栏
There's a button for opening.
侧边栏有自己的标题
We've got the title here for the side nav.
它的内容用列表的形式呈现
And then we've got the list of the side nav content.
从 CSS 上可以看出
In terms of the CSS, here's what we've got for the background.
背景是用 before 伪元素实现的
You see it's actually done with a before pseudo element.
背景色是透明度为
And you can see that it's got a background of black
40% 的黑色
with an opacity of 0.4.
对 opacity 设置了 will-change
We switched on will-change opacity
我们知道背景的透明度会发生改变
because we know we're going to be changing the opacity,
所以这么设置
so we're going to say will-change opacity.
别说成 will-change pasty 了
Didn't say will-change pasty.
完全两个意思
That would be a different thing entirely.
接着我们可以给 opacity 设置过渡了
Will-change opacity, and then we can set a transition of opacity
过渡函数用这个
with that curve.
看起来还不错
That looks quite nice.
300 毫秒
0.3 seconds.
速度也合适
Nice and quick.
现在要考虑如何让侧边栏可见
Then the other thing is when we set the side nav to visible,
我们将会用 JS 实现
which we're going to do with some JavaScripts,
还需要让 before 伪元素
and we can say to that before that we
渐渐出现
want you to fade up from an opacity of zero to an opacity of one.
侧边栏也同样如此
The same is pretty much true of the side nav itself.
看这
Here it is.
有个 box shadow
And you see it's got a box shadow.
所以侧栏边上会有一点点阴影
So we've got a nice little shadow on the side.
有趣的点在于 transform 的数值
The interesting thing is we have to transform it by,
在这个例子里我用了 102%  看上去不太整啊
in my case, 102%, which sounds really odd.
这么设置的原因在于那个阴影
But the reason is there's that shadow.
如果只是移动 100%
And if you just transform it 100% to the left,
就会看到侧边栏左边的部分阴影
you still see a little bit of shadow on the left-hand side.
所以需要把侧边栏推远一些  来解决这个问题
So if we just take it a little bit further, solves that problem.
侧边栏上还有些花样
The interesting thing about the side
它从屏幕左侧滑入的效果
nav itself, the one that comes in from the side,
是通过一个动画类实现的
is that it has a separate animatable class.
当用户拖拽的时候
The reason is I want to switch that off when they're
侧边栏没有动画
doing the drag motion and have it
而当侧边栏需要自动滑出的时候
on when they're doing the automated transition
才开启动画开关
from the side in and out.
所以我们用这个类来实现
So we use this class to basically say,
当动画被开启的时候  侧边栏自行滑入滑出
this is kind of-- it's doing the automatic transition,
关闭动画的时候  拖拽完成滑入滑出
or when it's off, it's going to be used for the dragging.
很棒
Cool.
JS 代码看这里
The JavaScript is over here.
所用的技巧和上次一样
And it's the same trick as last time.
我们将一堆事件绑定在 this 上
A bunch of event handlers that we bind on with this.
如果你不知道之前我是怎么做的
If you haven't seen why I do that,
回头看看 Swipeable Cards TL DW 那节的内容吧
go back and watch the Swipeable Cards TL;DW.
对这么处理事件句柄的原因  我解释了很多
I explain pretty much why I do this approach to my event handlers.
当然  你可以用别的方法
You don't have to take this approach,
只是在这个例子中  这种绑定方式执行地很顺畅
but it works pretty well for what I'm doing.
所以我们把所有 touch 事件都绑上
So we bind all those on.
这是侧栏显示和隐藏的代码
And you can see here we've got the show and the hide.
现在看这
Now, here's an interesting one.
我希望当你点击侧栏导航
I actually say that if you click on the side
还有点击我们在 Theory Corner 提到的容器元素时
nav, the containing element, the container from Theory Corner,
侧栏导航都会滑出屏幕  被隐藏起来
I want you to hide the side nav.
这行代码可以实现这个目标
Well, that will work kind of.
不过这么写以后  当点击导航中的内容时
But then if you click on something inside the side nav,
导航也会滑出屏幕
well, that's kind of weird because you've
毕竟导航确实是被点击到了  但这表现也太奇怪了
clicked on something in side nav, and it's going to dismiss.
解决上述问题的方法是
The way we get around that is we basically
当你点击侧边栏本身时  它滑出屏幕
say the side nav itself, that's going to hide it.
但当点击侧边栏内容时
But any clicks inside, we're going
要调用 BlockClicks 函数  看这
to call this BlockClicks function, which you can find down here.
它可以阻止冒泡
BlockClicks, all that does it stops the propagation.
BlockClicks 基本等同于对事件解绑
So it's almost like canceling the event.
只有在特定条件下你才会这么做
Now, you don't want to do this all the time.
而不是随随便便就去阻止冒泡
You only want to do it when it makes sense for your app.
在今天这个例子中  它也是有意义的
And it makes sense in my case, I think.
很好
So that's all good.
现在剩下的就是拖拽事件了
So I think all that's really left
让我们快速地过一下
is to just have a quick look at that drag motion.
如果你有印象的话  我们可以点击侧边栏
Now, if you remember, the drag motion looks like this.
也可以拖拽它
We can click, and we can drag.
如果只是把侧边栏拉出一点就松手
And if we just come away from the side a little bit
那它还会再次滑出屏幕
and let go, it dismisses the side nav.
来看看我们怎么实现的
So let's see how we code that in.
TouchStart 事件绑定在
Well, we have our onTouchStart here.
document 上
And basically, because this is bound to the document,
如果侧边栏没有滑出
I basically say if the side nav isn't open, bail.
就结束回调的执行
Don't hang around.
所以当你触发 TouchStart 事件时  就会执行该回调
So we're going to call this any time somebody hits TouchStart.
不过只有当侧边栏将会出现的时候  我们才需要做这样的处理
But we only want to deal with this if the side nav happens to be open.
接下来我们要做的
And what we do, very much the same kind
和在 Swipeable Cards 那节做几乎一模一样
of deal as the swipeable cards.
获取起始位置坐标的值
We capture the start position, and we copy that
赋值给当前位置
across to a current position.
接着在 TouchMove 中
And then in the TouchMove we basically
获取到手指的位移
figure out how far we moved, and then we
然后执行 transform
can apply a transform in a kind of game loop
在这  我们写了一个 update 函数
and update function, which you can see here.
实现了侧边栏从起始位置
There's the translate.
跟随手指滑动到
Current [INAUDIBLE] to start.
当前位置的效果
And then we apply it as a transform.
估计看过 Swipeable Cards 那节之后
If you've seen the Swipeable Cards,
你再看我刚刚说的这些  会觉得非常耳熟吧
this is all sounding very familiar, I'm sure.
老方法  但有效
But it works.
相当之有效
And it works really well.
最后在 TouchEnd 这块 我们添加了以下逻辑
The last thing is, on TouchEnd, we basically say,
如果手指移动的距离太短
if you translate it just a little bit to the left,
侧边栏还是不应该出现
hide the side nav, that works out really well for us.
在 onTouchMove 上还有一点需要注意
One other little thing to note is this, in terms of the OnTouch move,
默认情况下 Chrome 上模拟 TouchMove 时会有延迟
by default you'll get that throttle back in Chrome.
除非在 TouchMove 最开始被触发的时候
So you won't get them every frame,
阻止浏览器默认事件
unless the very first TouchMove event has
否则会掉帧
an event.preventdefault on it.
所以当发现手指位移小于 0 的时候
So what we do is we calculate the translate.
就说明 TouchMove 事件刚刚被触发
And we say, if it's less than zero,
接着用 event.preventdefault 阻止默认行为
as in you've started to move it, we prevent the default
之后浏览器就会及时响应 TouchMove 了
and that means it will get all the updates from then on.
搞定
So there you have it.
就是我们要的侧边栏
That's the side nav.
就用上面所说的这些方法
Pretty straightforward in terms of these things,
简单且效果好
but this works really well.
就算在移动设备上  也达到了 60 帧/秒
It works at 60 frames a second, even on a mobile device.
我们花了一个多小时直播实现这个侧边栏 如果你想看直播
If you haven't caught the livestream, again, it's about an hour long.
链接在下面的描述里
It's in the description below.
如果有时间
So have a look through that, and have a watch of that
也可以看看
if you've got a spare hour.
和往常的直播一样
Again, it's the usual kind of stuff.
你会看到各种 bug
You see all the bugs.
看到我和 Surma
You see all the chat.
在直播过程中的
You see all the discoveries and the kind of discussion
对话  探索和讨论
that [? Serma ?] and I had.
别忘了订阅我们
Don't forget to subscribe.
[CLICKING SOUND]
好了
Done.
我们下期再见
And I'll catch you next time.
如果你觉得这个节目有意思
If you, like me, like clicking on things, you can-- OK.
记得订阅哦
Hit the Subscribe.
哈哈哈
Ha, ha, ha.
这是直播
And there's the livestream.
[MUSIC PLAYING]